George C. Izenour architectural drawings, 1960-1978 02357
Eberly Family Special Collections Library
George C. Izenour architectural drawings
1960-1978
Eberly Family Special Collections Library
02357
1848 Items
George Charles Izenour (1912-2007) was an electronic stage lighting researcher, inventor, teacher, and consultant.
The collection contains drafts, final drawings, blueprints, and sepia prints on paper, mylar, and architectural vellum for theaters and performing arts centers designed by Izenour for communities and universities in Saudi Arabia, the United States, and Venezuela.
Biographical or Historical Note
George Charles Izenour was an electronic stage lighting researcher, inventor, teacher, and consultant. He wrote, "viewed in hindsight, my professional life as a theater engineer was virtually a continuous process of inventions and commercial licensing agreements for lighting control systems, flying systems, associated hardware, and controls. I have habitually, and for good reason, always reacted to the marketplace."
Izenour was born in New Brighton, Pennsylvania, July 24, 1912. He graduated from Wittenberg College, Springfield, Ohio, in 1936. In 1937 Izenour and his new bride moved to California and began his lifelong work in theater design and engineering with the Los Angeles project of the WPA Federal Theater as lighting director/designer. Izenour created for himself the profession of theater designer-engineer/consultant not only to design stage machinery and control systems but to design the theater itself. With a grant from the Rockefeller Foundation, he established the Electro-Mechanical Laboratory, Yale School of Drama, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, which he founded and directed from October 1939 until his retirement in 1977. For thirty-eight years Yale provided the building but Izenour had to raise funds for the operating budget of the laboratory and his salary. During World War II, Izenour was recruited by the Airborne Instruments Laboratory (AIL), a division of the Office of Scientific Research and Development, to work as a member of the Aircraft Compensation Group in developing the magnetic airborne detector for subsurface detection and sinking of submarines from aircraft. Here he became a self-taught mechanical designer and electronics engineer. Izenour left AIL in July 1946 and returned to New Haven in September to resume his own work.
In the laboratory, Izenour focused on developing a practical, moderately priced, remote electronic stage lighting intensity control system; he succeeded with an electronic console system for stage lighting (the world's first practical all-electronic switching and dimming circuit) in 1947. In May 1949 he was granted patents that protected both the electronic circuitry of the system and the mechanical design of the controls. Rather than selling the patents, he negotiated an exclusive commercial license to build and exploit commercially the electronic lighting intensity control system with Century Lighting Inc. and its executive vice president Ed Kook. Izenour became Century's field engineer as well as its systems designer. Black-and-white network television opened up opportunities for expansion in 1951 and Century negotiated for the Century-Izenour (C-I) system to be the approved method of lighting control for CBS and NBC productions. During the winter and early spring of 1948 Izenour designed and fabricated the first working scale model of the synchronous winch system, patented in 1959.
By the end of the 1950s Izenour added theater design and engineering consultant to his credentials. He participated as theater design-engineering and/or acoustical consultant in more than 100 buildings. He designed and built stage machinery for the Dallas, Texas theater center, 1959; Loeb Drama Center, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1960; drama center, University of South Florida, Tampa, 1961; and other multiple-use theater buildings.Izenour has published three books, Theater Design (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1977; reprint, Yale University Press, 1996), Theater Technology (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1988; reprint, Yale University Press, 1996), and Roofed Theaters of Classical Antiquity (New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1992).
To explain complex spatial relationships, Izenour and his draftsmen/graphic artists decided upon the longitudinal perspective section to capture the ambience of both stage and auditorium during performance, and orthographic isometric for structure and machinery. The Izenour Drawings of the Theater, an organized collection, came to the attention of the U.S. Information Service (USIS), the cultural branch of the Department of State. The USIS assembled a traveling exhibition of 100 of the drawings for showing throughout the world; the world premiere was held at the American Academy in Rome on 22 April 1977.
Realigned priorities at the Yale Drama School prompted Izenour to move his theater consulting practice off campus, retire from teaching, and sell the laboratory to the J. R. Clancy Company in Syracuse, New York in February 1977. George Izenour died 24 March 2007.
Collection Overview
The collection contains drafts, final drawings, blueprints, and sepia prints on paper, mylar, and architectural vellum for theaters and performing arts centers designed by Izenour for communities and universities in Saudi Arabia, the United States, and Venezuela.
Collection Arrangement
The drawings are organized into one series: Architectural Drawings.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Architectural; Theaters -- Designs and plans; Theaters -- Saudi Arabia -- Designs and plans; Theaters -- United States -- Designs and plans; Theaters -- Venezuela -- Designs and plans
- Architectural drawings, 1
  - Structural engineering drawings: William Penn High School, Wilson High School, Riverside Civil Auditorium, Krannert Center, Newton High School, Greenwich Country Day School, SUNY Stony Brook, West Virginia University, undated; Architectural (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Structural engineering drawings: Oral Roberts University, Longstreet Theatre (Univ. of SC), El Paso, Choate, Jesse Jones Hall, Eastman Theater, undated; Architectural (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lorain, Ohio blueprints: A1-24, E1-15, undated; Architectural (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lorain, Ohio blueprints: index, S1-11, SE1-13, P1-5, HVAC 1-9, FP1-3, undated; Architectural (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Cover, table of contents, architectural drawings A1-25, site drawings L1-3, 1976; Architectural (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Structural drawings blueprints S1-35, 1976; Architectural (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Structural drawings blueprints S36-50, 55-73, 1976; Architectural (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Architectural drawings A26-27, 29-81, 1976; Architectural (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Grand Rapids (MI) Convention/Entertainment Center: Electrical (E1-40) and Mechanical (ME 1-2) drawings, 1978; Architectural (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Grand Rapids (MI) Convention/Entertainment Center: Stage equipment (SE1-37) drawings, 1978; Architectural (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Grand Rapids (MI) Convention/Entertainment Center: HVAC, Fire Protection, Plumbing drawings, 1978; Architectural (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Grand Rapids (MI) Convention/Entertainment Center: Structural drawings (S1-16, 21-46, 51-56), 1978; Architectural (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, NYC: Vivian Beaumont Theater preliminary spacing use studies, 1960; Architectural (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, NYC: Vivian Beaumont Repertory Theater early lighting layout and studies, 1960; Architectural (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, NYC: Repertory Theater Museum and Library, 1960; Architectural (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, NYC: Electrical drawings, 1962; Architectural (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Damman Cultural Center, Saudi Arabia: Blueprints A36-67, 82, 1976-1977; Architectural (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Damman Cultural Center, Saudi Arabia: Blueprints Structural P-S part plan, 1976-1977; Architectural (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Damman Cultural Center, Saudi Arabia: Blueprints A6-35, 1976-1977; Architectural (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Damman Cultural Center, Saudi Arabia: Mylar drawings, 1976; Architectural (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ft. Wayne (IN) Fine Arts Foundation Theater of Performing Arts; BMW Museum picture screen, 1969, 1976; Architectural (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rodey Theater, University of New Mexico: Miscellaneous prints, 1971; Architectural (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Rodey Theater, University of New Mexico: Miscellaneous prints, 1971; Architectural (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rodey Theater, University of New Mexico: Original and sepia drawings, 1971; Architectural (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Longstreet Theatre, University of South Carolina: Original drawings, mostly obsolete, 1975; Architectural (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Longstreet Theatre, University of South Carolina: Blueprints, 1975; Architectural (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Longstreet Theatre, University of South Carolina: Original drawings, mostly obsolete, 1975; Architectural (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Longstreet Theatre, University of South Carolina: Original tracings, 1975; Architectural (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Electrical blueprints E1-30, 1976; Architectural (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Electrical blueprints E31-60, 1976; Architectural (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Electrical blueprints E61-90, 1976; Architectural (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Electrical blueprints E91-123, 1976; Architectural (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Blueprints, Mechanical, 1976; Architectural (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Blueprints, Drainage 1-17, 19-29, 1976; Architectural (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Blueprints, Piped Services P1-22, 1976; Architectural (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Blueprints, Food Service FS1-6, Air Conditioning M14-34, 1976; Architectural (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Mauch Chunk Opera House, Jim Thorpe, Pa., 1977; Architectural (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Fine Arts Center, Francis Marion College, Florence, SC: Blueprints S1-18, M1-13, 1978; Architectural (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Fine Arts Center, Francis Marion College, Florence, SC: Blueprints MP1-8, E1-19, Miscellaneous, 1978; Architectural (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Fine Arts Center, Francis Marion College, Florence, SC: Blueprints C1-2, A1-33, SE1-12, 1978; Architectural (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Fine Arts Center, SUNY Stony Brook: Design drawings and sepia prints, 1974; Architectural (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Grand Rapids (MI) Convention/Entertainment Center: Architectural drawings, 1978; Architectural (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Folly Theater, Kansas City, Mo.: Preliminary drawings, 1978; Architectural (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Standard GCI machinery and structural drawings, 1967; Architectural (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Cincinnati Gardens, Ohio, 1981; Architectural (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Mesa Community Center, Mesa, AZ: with Frank Lloyd Wright Foundation, 1976; Architectural (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Mexico City: Prints with overlays, 1977; Architectural (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Mexico City: Original vellum drawings, 1977; Architectural (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Mexico City: Sepia prints, 1977; Architectural (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Mexico City: Prints, some with overlays, 1977; Architectural (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Midland Center for the Arts, Midland, MI: Part A, Part C, Site plans, Floor plans, 1970; Architectural (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Teatro Teresa Carrena, Caracas, Venezuela: Prints 1-25, 1974; Architectural (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Teatro Teresa Carrena, Caracas, Venezuela: Prints 26-50, 1974; Architectural (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Milwaukee County (WI) War Memorial Center for the Performing Arts: Mylar drawings 1-7, 10-35, 1966; Architectural (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Secondary structures for stage and auditorium (Mylar negatives for printing), 1976; Architectural (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia Cultural Center: Stage equipment drawings (Mylar), 1976; Architectural (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - University of Nebraska: Design drawings, 1973; Architectural (Box 27, Folder 1)